Finding Aid for Bethlehem United Church of Christ (Ann Arbor, Mich.) Records 1833-1980
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Bethlehem United Church of Christ (Ann Arbor, Mich.) Records 1833-1980
Bethlehem United Church of Christ (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
Formerly the Bethlehem Evangelical Church. Minutes of annual congregational meetings, church council and board of trustees meetings, and treasurer's reports; records of the Frauen Vereines, or Ladies Aid Society, and Verein, or the Bethlehem Brotherhood, and the Jugend Vereins, or Youth Fellowship; fundraising materials, miscellaneous printed programs and newsletters, correspondence and clippings; treasurer's book, 1909-1916; and photographs.
86775; Ba 2; Ba outsize
7.5 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records were deposited by Bethlehem United Church of Christ (donor no. 5448 ) in three accessions (1980 and 1982-1983).
The record group is open for research.
The Bethlehem United Church of Christ was originally organized in 1833 as the First German Evangelical Society of Scio. Its first members were Wuerttemberger and Prussian immigrants who had come to Michigan in 1829, and who now organized themselves as the first German Protestant congregation in Michigan.
Friedrich Schmid was pastor of this congregation. Under his leadership, the members built a sanctuary which they referred to as Zion Church. Located one mile west of Ann Arbor, Zion Chapel was home to the congregation until 1849 at which time they moved into a church building located at First and Washington Streets in Ann Arbor to which they gave the name Bethlehem Church. In 1895, the congregation moved into a third structure on South Fourth Street. This building, though renovated and enlarged, has served the church to the present time (1980).
For the first few years of its existence, the church was without a constitution or any other formal organization. In 1838, the church received its first constitution where the evangelical character of its doctrinal beliefs was underscored. Because Schmid was a member of the Ohio Synod of the Lutheran Church, the church increasingly aligned itself with that denomination. In 1854, the name of the church was changed to the First German Evangelical Lutheran Church in Ann Arbor. When Schmid left the Synod in 1859, however, the church also dropped its association with the Lutheran Synod.
In 1945, the church voted to become a full member of the Evangelical and Reformed Church. When that denomination merged in 1958 with the Congregation-Christian churches, the Bethlehem church became the Bethlehem United Church of Christ.
In 1848, the church started a parish school to provide children with instruction in the German language, arithmetic, religion, singing, natural science, and geography. Completed in 1860, the schoolhouse was later enlarged in 1873 to accommodate the increase in enrollment.
In addition to this formal instruction the members of the congregation also participated in societies formed to bolster the social and financial needs of the church. One of the oldest, the Frauen Vereines, organized in 1871 as a result of agitation for support of a Sunday School library. The youth fellowship and Bethlehem Brotherhood also provided members of the congregation with an opportunity to become involved in church activities.
The Bethlehem United Church of Christ of Ann Arbor records span one hundred and forty years, from 1833 to 1973. The materials, partially in German, provide a good view of the congregation's history. Included are minutes and constitutions of the congregational annual meetings which span the period, 1855 to 1922. There are also records of the church council complete from 1897 to 1919, and financial records and treasurer's reports, and fund raising materials. There are records of several church organizations and photographs of church buildings and activities.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Bethlehem Evangelical Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Evangelical and Reformed Church--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; German Americans--Michigan.; United Church of Christ--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Societies and clubs.; Youth--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Bethlehem United Church of Christ (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Women--Religious life--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Youth--Religious life--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Material:
African Americans--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Churches.; Children.; Churches--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Evangelical and Reformed Church--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; German Americans--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Religion.; United Church of Christ--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Administrative Records
  - Historical materials, 2 folders (Box 1)
    (1-2)
  - Congregational constitution and annual meetings
    - 1833-1855 (Box 1)
      (2a)
    - 1855-1879 (Box 1)
      (3)
    - 1879-1897 (Box 1)
      (4)
    - 1898-1922 (Box 1)
      (5)
  - Minutes of the church council
    - 1897-1903 (Box 1)
      (6)
    - 1903-1909 (Box 1)
      (7)
    - 1910-1919 (Box 1)
      (8)
    - 1959-1966, 8 folders (Box 1)
      (8a-h)
  - Minutes of the board of trustees 1919-1924 (Box 1)
    (9)
  - Church constitutions 1833-1965 (Box 1)
    (10)
  - Constitution, and membership roster 1903-1944 (Box 1)
    (11)
  - Membership rosters undated, 1956-1961 (Box 1)
    (12)
  - Casual register for non-members 1872-1880 (Box 2)
    (13)
- Financial Records
  - Financial reports 1838-1859 (Box 2)
    (14)
  - Treasurer's book 1909-1916 (Box 2)
    (14a)
  - Treasurer's reports
    - 1921-1927 (Box 2)
      (15)
    - 1928-1930 (Box 2)
      (16)
    - 1931-1935 (Box 2)
      (17)
  - Printed financial reports
    - 1912-1915; and 1924-1944 (Box 2)
      (18)
    - 1944-1958 (Box 2)
      (19)
  - Financial records
    - 1923-1925 (Box 2)
      (20)
    - 1932-1938 (Box 2)
      (21)
    - 1939-1943 (Box 2)
      (21a)
    - 1944-1948 (Box 2)
      (21b)
    - 1949-1950 (Box 2)
      (22)
    - 1951-1956 (Box 2)
      (23)
    - 1961 (Box 2)
      (23a)
  - Receipts and miscellaneous financial records 1850-1930, 3 folders (Box 2)
    (24-26)
  - Dues and subscription list miscellanea 1850-1890, 2 folders (Box 2)
    (27-28)
  - Parish Hall pledge book 1930-1940 (Box 2)
    (29)
  - Benevolence fund
    - Special gifts 1939-1954 (Box 2)
      (30)
    - General
      - 1947-1950 (Box 2)
        (31)
      - 1950-1955 (Box 2)
        (32)
    - Miscellanea 1954 (Box 2)
      (33)
  - Improvement fund 1944-1955 (Box 2)
    (34)
  - Building fund campaign 1963 (Box 2)
    (35-36)
  - Building Committee Records 1963 (Box 2)
    (36a)
  - Capital funds campaign 1966 (Box 2)
    (37)
  - Pledge Records 1966-1967 (Box 2)
    (37a)
  - Architect Reports 1966 (Box 2)
    (37b)
  - Financial summaries 1833-1907 (Box 7)
    (94)
  - Estates record book (including treasurer's miscellaneous, 1917-1927) 1909-1921 (Box 7)
    (95)
  - New church building ledgers 1895-1896, 2 folders (Box 7)
    (96-97)
  - Treasurer's book 1881-1888 (Box 7)
    (98)
  - Treasurer's book 1902-1909 (Box 7)
    (99)
  - Treasurer's book 1948-1953 (Box 7)
    (100)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
    (101)
- Activities, newsletters, etc.
  - Church programs
    - Undated 1884-1908 (Box 3)
      (38)
    - 1909-1974 (Box 3)
      (39)
  - Catechism book 1893 (Box 3)
    (40)
  - Confirmation materials (Box 3)
    (41)
  - Anniversary materials 1883-1973 (Box 3)
    (42)
  - Histories of other churches in Ann Arbor (Box 3)
    (43)
  - Newsletters Bethlehem Visitor
    - September 1951-1953 (Box 3)
      (44)
    - 1954-1955 (Box 3)
      (45)
    - 1956-April 1958 (Box 3)
      (46)
- Church organizations
  The records of church-related societies include minutes, financial records, histories and membership lists of several church "vereins" and other member organizations. Of special note are the bound minutes and financial papers of the Frauen Vereines, or Ladies Aid Society. Written in German gothic script up until 1971, the society's records may prove useful in studies of women's history.
  - Verein. Bethlehem Brotherhood
    - History and membership lists 1905-1924 (Box 3)
      (47)
    - Minutes 1951-1962 (Box 3)
      (48)
    - Brotherhood Constitution and Membership List (Box 5)
      (93a)
    - Brotherhood Financial Records 1924-1947 (Box 5)
      (93b)
    - Brotherhood Financial Records 1947-1966 (Box 5)
      (93c)
    - Brotherhood Financial Records 1952-1962 (Box 5)
      (93d)
  - Jugend Vereins. Youth Fellowship
    - Constitution and membership lists undated (Box 3)
      (49)
    - Minutes 1950-1953 (Box 3)
      (50)
  - Regional Youth Federation 1902-1946 (Box 3)
    (51)
  - Frauen Vereines. Ladies Aid Society.
    (bound records in German)
    - Minutes and annual president's reports 1871-1921 (Box 3)
      (52)
    - Minutes and constitution 1904-1905 (Box 3)
      (53)
      (microfilm copy available)
    - Minutes 1905-1906 (Box 3)
      (54)
    - Attendance book 1906-1908 (Box 3)
      (55)
    - Minutes
      - 1906-1910 (Box 3)
        (56)
      - 1910-1914 (Box 3)
        (57)
      - 1914-1917 (Box 3)
        (58)
      - 1917-1920 (Box 3)
        (59)
      - 1920-1925 (Box 4)
        (60)
      - 1925-1929 (Box 4)
        (61)
    - Annual president's reports 1922-1939 (Box 4)
      (62)
    - Minutes
      - 1928-1931 (Box 4)
        (63)
      - 1931-1937 (Box 4)
        (64)
      - 1937-1941 (Box 4)
        (65)
      - 1941-1944 (Box 4)
        (66)
      - 1945-1948 (Box 4)
        (67)
      - 1949-1954 (Box 4)
        (68)
      - 1954-1959 (Box 4)
        (69)
      - 1959-1963 (Box 4)
        (70)
    - Constitution 1904 and minutes, 1963-1969 (Box 4)
      (71)
    - Minutes 1969-1971 (Box 4)
      (72)
    - Annual meetings minutes 1919-1937 (Box 4)
      (73)
    - Treasurer's book
      - 1898-1910 (Box 4)
        (74)
      - 1902-1904 (Box 4)
        (75)
      - 1910-1919 (Box 4)
        (76)
      - 1919-1939 (Box 4)
        (77)
      - 1939-1949 (Box 4)
        (78)
      - 1949-1962 (Box 4)
        (79)
      - 1962-1971 (Box 4)
        (80)
    - Dues book 1962-1971 (Box 5)
      (81)
    - Organ fund 1908 (Box 5)
      (82)
    - Memorial Fund 1922-1944 (Box 5)
      (83)
    - Kitchen fund 1923-1940 (Box 5)
      (84)
  - Church sewing group (Box 5)
    (85)
  - Women's guild dues book 1942-1947 (Box 5)
    (86)
  - Women's Auxiliary dues book 1947-1952 (Box 5)
    (87)
  - Women's Fellowship Minutes 1954-1965 (Box 5)
    (87a)
  - Women's Fellowship Minutes 1971-1975 (Box 5)
    (87b)
  - Women's Fellowship, Easter Breakfast 1958-1963 (Box 5)
    (87c)
  - Be Loyal Circle Minutes 1955-1980 (Box 5)
    (87d)
  - Be Loyal Circle Financial Records 1955-1980 (Box 5)
    (87e)
  - Minutes of the building committee 1872-1873 (Box 5)
    (88)
- Miscellanea
  - Reports and papers
    - 1925-1928 (Box 5)
      (89)
    - 1929-1934 (Box 5)
      (90)
    - 1940-1970 (Box 5)
      (90a)
  - Correspondence 1835-1925 (Box 5)
    (91)
  - Correspondence 1926-1939 (Box 5)
    (91a)
  - Correspondence 1940-1965 (Box 5)
    (91b)
  - Announcements and printed ephemera 1860-1925 (Box 5)
    (92)
  - Clippings, undated 1883-1973 (Box 5)
    (93)
  - Confirmation certificate of Oswals Herz 1890 (Folder 1)
  - Cemetery Records (Box 6)
    (see also First German Evangelischen Bethlehems Society, Ann Arbor, Cemetery plot map in oversize folder)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series include prints and slides of church activities (including worship services and the 1969 Black Manifesto episode), buildings, pastors and church members.
  - Activities
    - Black Manifesto (Charles Thomas) December 21, 1969 (Box 8)
    - Christmas Eve 1976 (Box 8)
      (color)
    - Cornerstone ceremony (Box 8)
      (slides)
    - Father-son picnic 1978 (Box 8)
    - Junior high retreat 1976 (Box 8)
    - School 1967 (Box 8)
    - School 1973 (Box 8)
    - Thanksgiving 1979 (Box 8)
    - Worship (Box 8)
    - Worship 1973 (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous, Adults (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous, Children (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
  - Buildings
    - First churches
      - Exterior (Box 8)
      - Interior (Box 8)
    - Present church
      - Break-in (Box 8)
      - Exterior (Box 8)
      - Exterior 1973 (Box 8)
      - Exterior (Box 8)
      - Interior, Older (Box 8)
      - Interior, Modern (Box 8)
      - Interior circa 1977 (Box 8)
      - Interior undated (Box 8)
    - School (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
  - Cemetery 1973 (Box 8)
  - Church pictorial history 1977-1978
    - Activities (Box 8)
    - Buildings (Box 8)
    - Groups (Box 8)
    - Groups (Box 8)
  - Groups
    - Identified (Box 8)
    - Unidentified (Box 8)
      (see also oversize folder)
    - Choir 1888 (Box 8)
    - Confirmation classes (Box 8)
    - School 1909 (Box 8)
  - Individuals
    - 19th century (Box 8)
    - 20th century (Box 8)
    - Staff 1970-1974 (Box 8)
    - Willimann, Rev. Orval (pastor); Rev. Samuel Andrew John (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
  - Negatives
    - Church pictorial history, Youth Club (Box 8)
    - Color (Box 8)
    - Father-son picnic 1978 (Box 8)
    - Old photos (Box 8)